Guide to the Janet Hamill archive, 1967-2010.
Hamill, Janet archive,
- Series IV: Photographs
  - Road trip, 1970s (Box 4, Folder 27)
    38 2 ¾ x 3 ½ inch photographs of JH and friends on a road trip.
  - Assorted snapshots, Date unknown (Box 4, Folder 28-30)
    13 small black and white and color photographs of various sizes, including travel shots of JH and friends, 72 color snapshots including many photos of JH artwork, 44 black and white snapshots, largely of JH’s home studio, Approx. 10 photographs of various sizes, including publicity photos.
  - Curtained object, Date unknown (Box 4, Folder 31)
  - Portrait of Janet Hamill, Date unknown (Box 11, Folder 1)
    11 x 14 inch black and white photograph. Signed by the photographer Judy Linn on verso.
- Series V: Audio and Visual items
  - Flying Nowhere, Date unknown; CD-1820 (Box 4, Folder 32)
  - Genie of the Alphabet, Date unknown; CD-1821 (Box 4, Folder 32)
  - Janet Hamill CAPS audio CD, April 2, 2010; CD-1822 (Box 4, Folder 32)
  - Bryan's Genie of the Alphabet visuals, Date unknown; CD-1823 (Box 4, Folder 32)
  - Moving Star, 2005; CD-1824 (Box 6, Folder 8)
  - Flying Nowhere, 2000; CD-1825 (Box 6, Folder 8)
  - Spoken Words live, Patti Smith group live, Moving Star live, April 1, 2001; CD-1826-1827 (Box 6, Folder 8)
  - Democracy Now! live, The Poetry Project live, the Poetry Project's 28th Annual New Year's Day Reading, Moving Star, 2001; CD-1828-1829 (Box 6, Folder 9)
  - Janet music, Moving Star, 2005; CD-1830-1832 (Box 6, Folder 9)
  - Moving Star, mixes, Spellbound, 2001, 2005; CD-1833-1838 (Box 6, Folder 10)
  - JH reading at Stockton State College, shot by Joel Sternfeld, ½ inch video, 1975; F-473 (Box 4, Folder 33)
  - Cable 6 News OCCC, November 5, 1992; V-6262 (Box 6)
  - Cyber Forest, Janet Hamill with Shrubs, 1997; V-6263 (Box 6)
  - Resist to be with the living, 2003; V-6264 (Box 6)
  - Janet Hamill and Moving Star, 2001; V-6265 (Box 6)
  - Patti Smith, Janet Hamill, Oliver Ray, Date unknown; V-6266 (Box 6)
  - 2 cassette tapes of JH reading, one marked St. Marks., December 1928; TR-9338-9339 (Box 4, Folder 34)
  - Janet Hamill, Moving Star, February 14, 1998; TR-9340 (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - Janet Hamill with Bob Torsello and Jay LoRubbio, August 1997; TR-9341 (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - The Poetry Project live, December 12, 1997; TR-9342 (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - Janet Hamill, Moving Star, Date unknown; TR-9343-9344 (Box 7, Folder 2)
  - Janet Hamill with Shrubs, 1997; TR-9345-9346 (Box 7, Folder 2)
  - Moving Star, Date unknown; TR-9347 (Box 7, Folder 3)
  - Moving Star demo, June 29, 1997; TR-9348 (Box 7, Folder 3)
  - Rube- Time Passages, Date unknown; TR-9349 (Box 7, Folder 3)
  - Janet Hamill mix tapes, Date unknown; TR-9350-9351 (Box 7, Folder 4)
  - Janet Hamill and Moving Star, Date unknown; TR-9352-9353 (Box 7, Folder 4)
  - Janet Hamill, Moving Star, Patti Smith rough mixes, 1995; TR-9354-9355 (Box 7, Folder 5)
  - Moving Star pre-production, Date unknown; TR-9356 (Box 7, Folder 5)
  - Janet Hamill and Moving Star, 1997-1998; TR-9357-9359 (Box 7, Folder 6)
- Series VI: Journals, Diaries and Notebooks
  - Notebook: Temple of Destruction, Mme. Bogart, 1976 (Box 4, Folder 35)
  - Two composition notebooks, 1979-1980 (Box 4, Folder 36)
  - Composition notebook, Csida, 1981 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Seven diaries, 1980-1985, 1999-2000 (Box 5, Folder 2-5)
  - Trip book, 1971 (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Histoire notebook, 1974 (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - Three notebooks, 2003, 2007 (Box 5, Folder 8-9)
  - Notebook and correspondence, Date unknown (Box 5, Folder 10)
  - Five notebooks, Date unknown (Box 5, Folder 11-12)
  - Notebook with sketches from Ken Tisa, Date unknown (Box 5, Folder 13)
  - Eight notebooks, Date unknown (Box 5, Folder 14)
    Includes notes on Subterraneous, Trans Atlantic and the Other Side, Seven Veils, Spell Bound, Flying Nowhere and Millennium
  - Nine Notebooks, Date unknown (Box 5, Folder 15-17)
  - Notebook with correspondence, photographs, and clippings, Date unknown (Box 6)
  - Aerial services notebook, Date unknown (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Three notebooks, Date unknown (Box 6, Folder 2-3)
- Series VII: Moving Star
  - Newspapers, Date unknown (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - Two T-shirts, Date unknown (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - Photographs, 1997-2005 (Box 6, Folder 6-7)
  - Janet Hamill and Moving Star flyers, December 27 (Box 7, Folder 7)
  - CD materials, 2001 (Box 7, Folder 8)
  - Bio, Date unknown (Box 7, Folder 9)
  - Tape artwork, Date unknown (Box 7, Folder 10)
  - Set lists, Date unknown (Box 7, Folder 11)
  - Flyers, Date unknown (Box 7, Folder 12)
  - Press, Date unknown (Box 7, Folder 13)
  - Photographs, Date unknown (Box 7, Folder 14)
  - Notebook, name tag, Date unknown (Box 7, Folder 15)
- Series VIII: Personal Effects and Miscellaneous Items
  - Mercury Records contract and correspondence, 1998 (Box 7, Folder 16)
  - BMI correspondence and records, 1998 (Box 7, Folder 17)
  - Bug Music, Date unknown (Box 7, Folder 18)
  - ASCAP materials, Date unknown (Box 7, Folder 19)
  - Record budget, Date unknown (Box 7, Folder 20)
  - AFTRA membership, 1999 (Box 7, Folder 21)
  - Goshen Public Library materials, 1980s (Box 7, Folder 22)
  - Application, 1986 (Box 7, Folder 23)
  - Independent Republican newspapers, 1997-2000 (Box 7, Folder 24-27)
  - Goshen Public Library Poetry materials, including photographs, 1998-2000 (Box 7, Folder 28)
  - Visiting Poetry Project, 2000 (Box 7, Folder 29)
  - Wedding cards, 1980 (Box 8, Folder 1)
  - Miscellaneous, including stamp, Date unknown (Box 8, Folder 2-5)
  - Newsletters and papers, Date unknown (Box 8, Folder 6-8)
- Series IX: Artwork by others
  - Benowitz print, 1973 (Box 8, Folder 9)
  - Ken Tisa, Date unknown (Box 11, Folder 2)
    3 original ink drawings, signed by the artist. Sizes vary, approx.5 ½ x 7 inches. 1 print of one of the ink drawings, 8 ½ x 11 inches. Color drawing of a pyramid shape with collaged color snapshot of pink pelicans, titled “Paradise.” Signed and inscribed by the artist, approx. 8 x 11 inches
  - Joel Sternfeld "Bar/Man in Hat/Young Girl's Hair", 1976-1977 (Box 12, Folder 2)
    Color photograph of inside a bar in the “Deep South”, 15 ¾ x 11 ½ inches in a 20 x 16 inch mat. Both the photo and mat are soiled. Signed by the artist.
  - Maureen Owen, Date unknown (Box 12, Folder 2)
    “reading moonlight or reading on the moon” broadside, signed and inscribed by the poet, 12 x 16 inches.
- Series X: Patti Smith
  - Subseries Xa: Correspondence with Janet Hamill
    - Miscellaneous correspondence and photographs, 1970s (Box 8, Folder 10)
    - Manuscript Music book, 1970 (Box 8, Folder 11)
      Written on cover: “Featuring old correspondence Note: new correspondence can be designated by blue fountain pen,” return address at the Hotel Chelsea, and “Patricia L Smith.” There are also several stickers on the cover. Inside are handwritten poems, thoughts, songs, and lists written to JH. Items laid in at different pages include: two poems, “exclusive pix of Howie [Howard Michaels],” ad for Jesse Winchester album, and clipping of James Dean on newsprint.
    - Correspondence, 1970; 3 TLS, 6 ALS (Box 8, Folder 12)
      Includes photographs, poems, and a lock of Janet's brother's hair.
    - Flyer for Gerard Malanga and Smith reading, February 10, 1971 (Box 8, Folder 13)
    - Letter on stationary from the White House, London, February 23, 1971; ALS (Box 8, Folder 13)
    - Piece of cloth with "Chelsea" written on it with envelope, April 9, 1971 (Box 8, Folder 13)
    - Clipping from The Herald on Female Super 8, May 16, 1971 (Box 8, Folder 13)
    - Letter, 1971; ALS (Box 8, Folder 13)
    - Letter, March 31, April 7, 1972; 2 ALS (Box 8, Folder 14)
      Written on the back of the typescript of “Piano,” a Smith poem, with some handwriting also on it. The envelope has a sticker of a duck.
    - Letters, June 5, 1973; 2 ALS (Box 8, Folder 15)
      Written on the back of a photocopy of the corrected cover layout for PS’s Witt, published by Gotham Book Mart, 1973. There is also some writing on the photocopy.
    - Letter, February 11, 1974; ALS (Box 8, Folder 16)
      Written on “Correograma” stationery and sent from Mexico.
    - Letters, August 26, December 5, 1975; 2 ALS, TLS, MS (Box 8, Folder 17)
    - Letters, 1980; 5 ALS, ACS, APCS (Box 8, Folder 18)
      Includes a Polaroid photograph of Janet
    - Letters, 1971; ALS, APCS (Box 8, Folder 19)
      With photograph of "Smith Kitchen"
    - Letters and Christmas Card, 1989; 4 ALS (Box 8, Folder 20)
      With photograph of Smith children.
    - Letters, 1990; 21 ALS (Box 8, Folder 21-22)
      Many include children's scribbles.
    - Letters, 1991; 14 ALS, APCS, MS (Box 8, Folder 23-24)
      "Gale" manuscript, clippings from papers.
    - Letters, 1992; 9 ALS, 3 APCS (Box 8, Folder 25)
      With manuscript of "February Snow".
    - Letters, 1993; 8 ALS, ACS (Box 8, Folder 26)
      With manuscript of "The Coral Sea" and "The Writer's Song"
    - Letters, 1994; 5 ALS (Box 8, Folder 27)
      2 copies of the Memorial Service announcement card for Fred “Sonic” Smith,and 2 copies of the Mariners’ Church of Detroit Memorial Service program. Includes some photographs.
    - Letter, 1995; ALS (Box 8, Folder 28)
      With memorial cards.
    - Napkin with note to Joe Csida, 1997 (Box 8, Folder 29)
    - Letters, 1998; 2 ALS (Box 8, Folder 30)
    - Letter, 1999; APCS, card (Box 8, Folder 31)
    - Woolgathering, 1990s; 3 MS (Box 8, Folder 32)
    - Letters, 2002; APCS, ACS (Box 8, Folder 33)
      Includes laminated memorial card for Beverly Williams Smith, PS’s mother; black ribbon; and folded memorial card.
    - Correspondence, 2004-2005; 4 EM, 1 ALS, MS (Box 8, Folder 34)
      Manuscripts of poems that became Auguries of Innocence, 2005, 53 pp. Many corrections, in the hand of JH, throughout.
    - Miscellaneous, Date unknown (Box 8, Folder 35)
  - Subseries Xb: Photographs of Patti Smith
    - Photographs, 1969-1995 (Box 8, Folder 36)
    - Photographs, 2005-2008, undated (Box 8, Folder 37)
  - Subseries Xc: Artwork by Patti Smith
    - Photographs, some for Body of Water, 2005-2006 (Box 8, Folder 38)
      A 4 7/8 x 7 ½ inch wood (cigar?) box that PS created after visiting Federico García Lorca’s niece and handling an “original” copy of Poeta en Nueva York. PS presented the box to JH. It contains items that she brought back from Spain and includes: linen gloves that PS wore while handling the García Lorca manuscript, an unburned votive candle; a dried flower; a picture of García Lorca; a paper lace doily; a British pound coin; a Spanish postcard from 1903 of an unidentified woman; and a slip of paper with “Octubre 2007” printed on it.
    - "Lorca Box", 2007 (Box 8)
  - Subseries Xd: Just Kids Manuscripts and Notes
    - Early handwritten notes, ca. 1994 (Box 9, Folder 1)
      Inserted in back of pad is handwritten manuscript on notebook graph paper of the poem “Wild Leaves” that appears only in the paperback edition of Just Kids. Also inserted in back are a color photocopy of six SX-70 photographs of Jesse Smith (?) in a graveyard with Smith family gravestones and a photocopy from parts of a Los Angeles Times article about Robert Mapplethorpe’s artwork.
    - Handwritten notes on graph paper, Date unknown (Box 9, Folder 2)
      Including chronologies, journal entries, letters (never sent), dreams and poems.
    - Notes for Monday's Children, Date unknown (Box 9, Folder 3)
    - Outline Monday's Children, Date unknown (Box 9, Folder 4)
    - Original manuscript with handwritten notes, Date unknown (Box 9, Folder 5)
    - Monday's Children notes, Date unknown (Box 9, Folder 6)
      Notes, questions, suggestions for sections and areas needing to be developed, including tone and focus of the book. Also noted are new sections, additional writing and other changes that have been done to the manuscript.
    - Manuscript copies, Date unknown (Box 9, Folder 7-8)
    - Outline Monday's Children, Date unknown (Box 9, Folder 9)
    - Bound manuscript, May 2004 (Box 9, Folder 10)
    - Emails and manuscripts, Date unknown (Box 9, Folder 11)
    - Notes and drafts, Date unknown (Box 9, Folder 12)
    - Picturing Robert manuscripts with notes, Date unknown (Box 9, Folder 13-14)
    - Letters to Betsy Lerner, 1998 (Box 9, Folder 15)
    - "Monday's Children" notes, Date unknown (Box 9, Folder 16)
    - Notes, Date unknown (Box 9, Folder 17)
    - "Just Kids" notes, Date unknown (Box 9, Folder 18)
    - Hotel Chelsea folder with typed manuscript pages, Date unknown (Box 9, Folder 19)
    - "Separate Ways Together" with notes and writings, Date unknown (Box 9, Folder 20)
    - Typed manuscripts, Date unknown (Box 9, Folder 21)
    - Floppy disk of stories, Date unknown (Box 9, Folder 22)
  - Subseries Xe: Assorted Materials
    - "East Side Sutra: View from a Window", The Press, October 1974 (Box 9, Folder 23)
      A complete issue of The Press, a monthly New York City newspaper. It contains a section “The East Village: The Pangs of Rebirth,” with this Patti Smith contributed article.
    - "Return of Patti Smith", The Press, 1995 (Box 9, Folder 24)
      With an issue of Vanity Fair
    - "Return of Patti Smith", The Village Voice, 1995 (Box 11, Folder 3)
    - Clarinet reed, 2000 (Box 9, Folder 25)
      Smith's reed from when she played with JH and Moving Star
    - "A Pythagorean Traveler" exhibition, 2006-2007 (Box 9, Folder 26)
      Announcement card for Patti Smith solo exhibition at the Robert Miller Gallery. The exhibition included recent photographs as well as an installation piece, a composite of objects, drawings, and a vintage silk cloth inscribed by the arti
    - Just Kids excerpt in Rolling Stone, 2010 (Box 9, Folder 27)
    - Forward to Nostalgia of the Infinite, Date unknown (Box 9, Folder 28)
    - Postcard of Jean-Paul Belmondo sent to Janet Hamill, 1973 (Box 10, Folder 9)
    - Photograph of Hamill and Smith taken at the Village Gate, 1977 (Box 10, Folder 9)
    - Framed self-portrait of Smith and Hamill, 1966 (Box 12)
      Drawing with colored pencil of PS with JH, 1966. This was made while JH was living with PS’s family. It is inscribed by PS: “Chaps, ltd. 1966. With love to Chaps.” According to JH, this drawing had been in the possession of Robert Mapplethorpe for over twenty years. It was given back to PS, by his estate, after his death. PS later gave the drawing to JH. 10 x 13 drawing in 19 x 23 inch frame.
  - Subseries Xf: Robert Mapplethorpe
    - Invitation to gallery opening Untitled, January 1, 1973 (Box 9, Folder 29)
    - Memorial card with Patti Smith poem, 1989 (Box 9, Folder 29)
    - List of speakers at Mapplethorpe memorial, May 22, 1989 (Box 9, Folder 29)
    - Invitation to a ceremony commemorating the anniversary of Mapplethorpe's cancelled exhibit, June 12, 1995 (Box 9, Folder 29)
  - Subseries Xg: Performances and Events with Patti Smith and Janet Hamill
    - Cutty Sark Hart Crane handbill, February 4, 1974 (Box 9, Folder 30)
      Handbill, for a reading with Anne Powell, Juan Hamill (Janet Hamill) and Patti Smith at the Razor Gallery. Also included is the original collage artwork for the handbill.
    - Summerstage, July 25, 1995 (Box 9, Folder 31)
      JH read her poems as the opening act for Patti Smith’s Central Park Summerstage appearance. Included are: an artist’s agreement, posters, t-shirt, Neil Strauss’s New York Times review, clippings, and poems with handwritten notes that JH read.
    - Art Show and Poetry Reading, October 8-November 5, 1995 (Box 9, Folder 32-34)
      JH and Patti Smith were brought to Boston by their old friend Patti Hudson. This was Smith’s first Boston appearance in 16 years. They did an evening of readings together and had an exhibition. Smith showed Polaroids at the Art Market Gallery, and JH showed her watercolors. Included are: publicity around the events, some correspondence and a t-shirt made for the event.
    - Liss Ard Festival, Co. Cork, Ireland, September 1997 (Box 9, Folder 35-40)
      Patti Smith was the festival’s first director in 1997. JH participated in the festival and did several readings, including a reading with Patti Smith and Nick Cave. Includes: photographs of the event (approx 70 color snapshots and 11 8 x 10 inch black and white photographs); itinerary; correspondence; tshirts; “The Gardens Voice: Liss Ard 97”, and press folder.
    - Liss Ard poster, 1997 (Mapcase-folder 1)
    - People's Poetry Gathering, April 1, 2001 (Box 10, Folder 1)
      JH and Moving Star opened for Patti Smith and her Band. Includes: participant badge; letter of agreement; some correspondence; and programs for the event.
    - Strange Messenger, opening party and reading, September 2002 (Box 10, Folder 2)
    - Warhol Museum Performance, Oct 18, 2002 (Box 10, Folder 3)
      Flyer for JH and Moving Star performance at the Warhol Museum. At the time “Strange Messenger: The Art of Patti Smith” was on also display at the Museum. Also included in the folder is JH agreement with the Museum, correspondence and other items.
    - Meltdown festival, June 2005 (Box 10, Folder 4)
      The 2005 Meltdown was directed by Patti Smith. She performed along with many others, including JH, Antony and the Johnsons, Beth Orton, Billy Bragg, Cat Power, Joanna Newsom, John Cale, Lenny Kaye, Martha Wainwright, Marc Almond, Richard Hell, Roy Harper, Sinéad O'Connor, Television, and Yoko Ono. JH performed with John Giorno and also discussed her work with Smith. Included are: the event’s program, stage pass, correspondence, letter of agreement, publicity, and 2 handwritten manuscripts in JH’s hand.
    - Summerstage, 2005 (Box 10, Folder 5)
      JH and Moving Star were the opening act for Patti Smith’s 2005 Central Park Summerstage appearance. Included are: stage pass, correspondence, set list and 34 snapshots of the event.
    - Latitude Festival, 2006 (Box 10, Folder 6)
      Both Patti Smith and JH performed at the first annual Latitude Festival. Included are a UK newspaper with an article about the festival and 2 performer wristbands.
    - An Intimate Evening with Patti Smith and Janet Hamill, March 2, 2008 (Box 10, Folder 7)
      Both Smith and JH attended Rowan when it was named Glassboro State College. Included are: program, set list, press release, and photocopies of snapshots.
  - Subseries Xh: Audio Material
    - "Horses" vinyl record, Date unknown (Box 11, Folder 4)
      Arista Records, Test Pressing, Demonstration Copy, Not for Sale. From the Wartoke Concern, Inc
    - "Horses" vinyl record, Date unknown (Box 11, Folder 5)
      Arista Records; initial release without sleeve. From the Wartoke Concern, Inc
    - "Radio Ethiopia" vinyl record, Date unknown (Box 11, Folder 6)
      Arista Records, Promotional Copy, Not for Sale. From the Wartoke Concern, Inc
    - Test pressing for Velvet Underground album "The Velvet Underground and Nico", Date unknown (Box 11, Folder 7)
      From the Wartoke Concern, Inc
    - "Radio Ethiopia" vinyl record, September 18, 1976 (Box 11, Folder 8)
      Arista Records, Demonstration Copy, Not for Sale; in original sleeve; cover photo by Judy Linn. Liner notes signed and dated by Patti Smith.
    - "Easter" vinyl record, Date unknown (Box 11, Folder 9)
      Arista Records, original release in original sleeve; not inscribed; cover photo by Lynn Goldsmith. Liner notes signed by PS and also with the mark of a cross in her hand.
    - "People Have the Power" vinyl record, Date unknown (Box 11, Folder 10)
      Arista Records, loaned for promotion only, not for sale; in original sleeve; not inscribed; cover photo by Robert Mapplethorpe.
    - "Dream of Life" vinyl record, Date unknown (Box 11, Folder 11)
      Arista Records; original release in original sleeve; not inscribed; cover photo by Robert Mapplethorpe.
    - "Hey Joe/Piss Factory" 45, Date unknown (Box 10, Folder 8)
      Sire Records, Special Collector’s Edition; sleeve only; inscribed; cover photo Sandy Daley.
  - Subseries Xi: Posters and Broadsides
    - Patti Smith "Poetry and Music", July 27, 1995 (Box 12, Folder 1)
      With Janet Hamill, Lenny Kaye, and Kimberly Smith, signed by all of the performers, 14 x 22 inches.
    - Poster, 1997 (Box 12, Folder 1)
      Patti Smith and Special Guests, Nick Cave, Donal Dineen, David Gray, Janet Hamill, Ron Sexsmith, Liss Ard Festival, Co. Cork, Ireland, Sep 3–7, 1997, 33 x 23 ½ inches.
    - "Ps/alm revisited for William Burroughs", 1995 (Box 12, Folder 1)
      Letterpress printed by Leslie Miller at The Grenfell Press for Hanuman Books, 12 ½ x 15 inches.
    - "A Small Entreaty", 1995 (Box 12, Folder 1)
      Letterpress printed by Leslie Miller at The Grenfell Press for Hanuman Books.
SEPARATED MATERIAL
Books - cataloged individually in the Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections
Fleurs du Mal: in Pattern and Prose, by Charles Baudelaire
The Letters of Charles Baudelaire to his Mother, 1833-1866, by Charles Baudelaire
Genioy Figura de Jorge Luis Borges, by Alicia Jurado